A Guide to the Commonwealth Fund records, Program for the Prevention of Delinquency, SG 1, Series 29 FA301
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund records, Program for the Prevention of Delinquency, SG 1, Series 29
1921-1927
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund
FA301
1.76 Cubic Feet 4 boxes
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical/Historical note
The Commonwealth Fund was established in 1918 with an endowment of $10 million from Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness for "benevolent, religious, educational and like purposes." The early grants supported a variety of programs while generally promoting welfare, especially child welfare. Several grants were made in the field of medical research, but the Board of Directors decided in 1920 that this field was already sufficiently supported by other philanthropic organizations.
Despite this decision, by the mid-1920s the chief interest of the Fund had become public health, including mental hygiene, community health, rural hospitals, medical research, and medical education. Other grant areas included war relief, educational and legal research, child welfare, and international medical fellowships.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IX; IV 4B 4
Scope and Contents note
The Commonwealth Fund officially adopted its "Program for the Prevention of Delinquency" on November 9, 1921. The program consisted of four divisions: Division I, The New York School of Social Work; Division II, The National Committee for Mental Hygiene-Division of the Prevention of Delinquency; Division III, The National Committee on Visiting Teachers-Public Education Association of New York; and Division IV, The Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (JCMPD).
The New York School of Social Work established in 1919 a Department of Mental Hygiene, whose didactic objective was to give the school's students a better insight into human nature and conduct in health and disease. In order to give students opportunities for the actual study and management of problems in human maladjustment, in close affiliation with professional psychiatrists, the school maintained a Bureau of Children's Guidance in conjunction with the Neurological Department of Vanderbilt Clinic. The school also granted fellowships to qualified students and professionals to attend classes and seminars in child guidance. Most of the surviving records consist of financial statements and correspondence relating to budgets, and the Annual Reports from the Bureau of Children's Guidance (1922-1927). Division I of the Delinquency Program was created on December 1, 1921 and began operations on February 1, 1922. Division I formally ceased operations on July 30, 1927.
The National Committee for Mental Hygiene was founded in 1909 and incorporated in 1916. Through funding by the Commonwealth Fund, the Committee's Division on the Prevention of Delinquency held Child Guidance Clinics in several cities, most notably Norfolk, Virginia; Dallas, Texas; and St. Louis, Missouri. The National Committee also sponsored a fellowship program. All the documents concern budgetary matters.
Division III of the Commonwealth Fund's program, The National Committee of Visiting Teachers maintained a series of clinics for visiting teachers, held grading demonstrations throughout the United States and furnished visiting teachers to many school districts. The work funded by the Commonwealth Fund was directed through the auspices of the Public Education Association of The City of New York, which was founded in 1895 and incorporated in 1899. After the Delinquency program ended, the Visiting Teachers Program continued under the general guidelines of the mental hygiene program. Demonstrations were maintained and contact and supervision of the permanent work established under the demonstrations was provided. Assistance and advice regarding visiting teaching problems and programs was given to cities requesting the same. The Commonwealth Fund granted money to the Visiting Teachers until June 30, 1930. The records are all of a financial nature and reflect the Committee's activities both as a component of the Delinquency Program and as an independent body. The National Committee on Visiting Teachers disbanded on June 30, 1931.
The Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (JCMPD) was incorporated on February 22, 1922 under the laws of the State of New York, and served as a coordinating agent for the Juvenile Delinquency Program and its member groups. The publication and dissemination of information and literature on juvenile delinquency and child guidance was a primary function of the JCMPD. The name of the Committee is misleading since the majority of its work entailed the directing of a program of mental health, child guidance clinics, visiting teachers, and the training of individuals for competency in child guidance. The Committee's documents include minutes of the organization, both before and after the incorporation of the Committee, which transcribe the decisions of the Board of Directors, the Executive Committee, and the corporation as a whole. Financial records and the Committee's newsletter are also found in this collection. After the dissolution of its charter in 1927, many of the Committee's members formed the nucleus of the Commonwealth Fund's new Division of Publications, a not too unlikely move given the Committee's prior active participation in this area.
Individuals associated with the Commonwealth Fund's Program for the Prevention of Delinquency include Barbara S. Quin, Bernard Glueck, Howard W. Nudd, Barry C. Smith, Porter R. Lee, Graham R. Taylor, Julia C. Lathrop, Frankwood E. Williams, Henry C. Morrison, Thomas W. Salmon, Mildred C. Scoville and Ralph P. Truitt.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Commonwealth Fund records include:
FA247 Commonwealth Fund Harkness House drawings
FA276 Commonwealth Fund records, Annual Reports, SG 1, Series 4
FA277 Commonwealth Fund records, Archives/Library, SG 1, Series 5
FA278 Commonwealth Fund records, Austrian Program, SG 1, Series 6
FA279 Commonwealth Fund records, Board of Directors, SG 1, Series 7
FA280 Commonwealth Fund records, Capital Grants, SG 1, Series 8
FA281 Commonwealth Fund records, Child Health Demonstrations, SG 1, Series 9
FA282 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Community Clinics, SG 1, Series 10
FA283 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Health Studies, SG 1, Series 11
FA284 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Public Health, SG 1, Series 12
FA285 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Publications, SG 1, Series 13
FA286 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Rural Hospitals, SG 1, Series 14
FA287 Commonwealth Fund records, Educational Research, SG 1, Series 15
FA288 Commonwealth Fund records, English Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 16
FA289 Commonwealth Fund records, Finance Committee, SG 1, Series 17
FA290 Commonwealth Fund records, Grants, SG 1, Series 18
FA291 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Family, SG 1, Series 19
FA292 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, SG 1, Series 20
FA428 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, Fellows Reports, SG 1, Series 20A
FA293 Commonwealth Fund records, Institute for Child Guidance, SG 1, Series 21
FA294 Commonwealth Fund records, Interface Program, SG 1, Series 22
FA295 Commonwealth Fund records, Legal Research Program, SG 1, Series 23
FA296 Commonwealth Fund records, Living at Home Program, SG 1, Series 24
FA297 Commonwealth Fund records, Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 25
FA298 Commonwealth Fund records, Miscellaneous - unprocessed
FA299 Commonwealth Fund records, Personnel - unprocessed
FA300 Commonwealth Fund records, Pilgrim Trust, SG 1, Series 28
FA301 Commonwealth Fund records, Program for the Prevention of Delinquency, SG 1, Series 29
FA302 Commonwealth Fund records, Reference Files, SG 1, Series 30
FA303 Commonwealth Fund records, Reports of the General Director, SG 1, Series 31
FA304 Commonwealth Fund records, Treasurer, SG 1, Series 32
FA305 Commonwealth Fund records, Turndown Lists, SG 1, Series 33 - unprocessed
FA306 Commonwealth Fund records, Vertical File (R. Fitz), SG 1, Series 34 - unprocessed
FA307 Commonwealth Fund records, Visual Materials, SG 1, Series 35
FA389 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Historical Files, SG 1, Series 1
FA390 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Officers Files, SG 1, Series 2
FA429 Commonwealth Fund records, President, Margaret E. Mahoney, SG 2, Series 1
FA430 Commonwealth Fund records, Book Program, SG 2, Series 2
Mental health; Medicine -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Medical education; Legal research; Medicine, Rural; Medical research; Public health; New York (State); United States; Public welfare; War relief; Law; Legal issues; Education, Rural; Hygiene; Child psychology; Child welfare; New York (N.Y.); Child mental health; Social Science Research Council; Harvard University; Harkness, Anna M. Richardson; Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman; Harkness, Edward Stephen; Harkness, Charles W.; Phillips Exeter Academy; Columbia University; Yale University
- New York School for Social Work (Division I) - Bureau of Children's Guidance - Annual Report, December 1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- New York School for Social Work (Division I) - Bureau of Children's Guidance - Annual Report, 1923-1924 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- New York School for Social Work (Division I) - Bureau of Children's Guidance - Annual Report, 1924-1925 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- New York School for Social Work (Division I) - Bureau of Children's Guidance - Annual Report, September 1926 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- New York School for Social Work (Division I) - Bureau of Children's Guidance - Glueck Report, October 1923 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- New York School for Social Work (Division I) - Financial Statements and Correspondence, 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- New York School for Social Work (Division I) - Financial Statements and Correspondence, 1925-1927 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- New York School for Social Work (Division I) - Preliminary Operating Report, 1921-1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- The National Committee for Mental Hygiene (Division II) - Financial Statements and Correspondence, 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- The National Committee for Mental Hygiene (Division II) - Financial Statements and Correspondence, March-December, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- The National Committee for Mental Hygiene (Division II) - Financial Statements and Correspondence, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Chase Report (Josephine Chase - "Thirty Visiting Teachers in Thirty Counties"), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Chase Report (Josephine Chase - "Thirty Visiting Teachers in Thirty Counties"), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Confidential Report - Volume I - "The Work as a Whole, November 9, 1921-June 30, 1927", 1921-1927 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Confidential Report - Volume II - "The Work in Each Demonstration Center, November 9, 1921-June 30, 1927", 1921-1927 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Confidential Report - Volume II - "The Work in Each Demonstration Center, November 9, 1921-June 30, 1927", 1921-1927 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Confidential Report - Volume II - "The Work in Each Demonstration Center, November 9, 1921-June 30, 1927", 1921-1927 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Confidential Report - Volume III - "The Work in Each Demonstration Center, November 9, 1921-June 30, 1927", 1921-1927 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Confidential Report - Volume III - "The Work in Each Demonstration Center, November 9, 1921-June 30, 1927", 1921-1927 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Confidential Report - Volume III - "The Work in Each Demonstration Center, November 9, 1921-June 30, 1927", 1921-1927 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Confidential Report - Volume III - "The Work in Each Demonstration Center, November 9, 1921-June 30, 1927", 1921-1927 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Confidential Report - Volume IV - "The Work in Each Demonstration Center, November 9, 1921-June 30, 1927", 1921-1927 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Confidential Report - Volume IV - "The Work in Each Demonstration Center, November 9, 1921-June 30, 1927", 1921-1927 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Confidential Report - Volume IV - "The Work in Each Demonstration Center, November 9, 1921-June 30, 1927", 1921-1927 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Financial Statements and Correspondence, 1922-1923 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Financial Statements and Correspondence, 1924-1925 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Financial Statements and Correspondence, 1926-1927 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Financial Statements and Correspondence, 1928-1929 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Financial Statements and Correspondence, 1930-1931 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Nudd Report (Howard W. Nudd - "A National Program on Visiting Teachers"), 1930 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- National Committee on Visiting Teachers (Division III) - Nudd Report (Howard W. Nudd - "A National Program on Visiting Teachers"), 1930 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (Division IV) - Charter, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 32)
  Scope and Contents note
  By-Laws/Incorporation January 23, 1922; Amendment May 24, 1922.
- Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (Division IV) - Charter - Dissolution, November 28, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (Division IV) - Chronology, 1921-1922 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (Division IV) - Financial Statements and Correspondence, 1922-1923 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (Division IV) - Financial Statements and Correspondence, 1924-1925 (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (Division IV) - Financial Statements and Correspondence, 1926-1927 (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (Division IV) - Minutes, November-December, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (Division IV) - Minutes, January-March, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (Division IV) - Minutes, April-December, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 40)
- Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (Division IV) - Minutes, 1923-1924 (Box 4, Folder 41)
- Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (Division IV) - Minutes, 1925-1926 (Box 4, Folder 42)
- Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (Division IV) - Newsletters (#1-5), June-October, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 43)
- Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (Division IV) - Newsletters (#6-10), January-December, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 44)
- Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (Division IV) - Newsletters (#11-18), January-December, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (Division IV) - Newsletters (#19-24 and #28), January-September, 1925 and January 1926 (Box 4, Folder 46)
- Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (Division IV) - Walter Study (Henriette R. Walter - "The Relation Between Vocational Guidance and Visiting Teaching"), 1925 (Box 4, Folder 47)
- Joint Committee on Methods of Preventing Delinquency (Division IV) - Walter Study (Henriette R. Walter - "The Relation Between Vocational Guidance and Visiting Teaching"), 1925 (Box 4, Folder 48)